Finding Aid for Dorothy H. Coons papers, 1936-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dorothy H. Coons papers 1936-1987
Coons, Dorothy H., 1914-
(in 3 boxes)
2.5 linear feet
90138 Aa 2
Gerontologist at the Institute of Gerontology of the University of Michigan, specializing in Alzheimer's Disease and the training and education of people working with the elderly. Professional papers, including correspondence, subject files, papers and reports, and files relating to workshops and symposia attended; Alzheimer's Disease research files; photographs; and other audio-visual materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Dorothy Coons (donor no. 7740 ) in October 1989.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Dorothy H. Coons has been associated with the University of Michigan Institute of Gerontology (IoG) since 1939, when, as a graduate student, she became a research assistant in the Administrative Office of the Institute for Human Adjustment, precursor to the IoG. Her involvement with the institute subsequently spanned four decades, during which time she was active in programming and research. Coons played a leading role in several major research projects sponsored by the institute, including the Ypsilanti State Hospital Project started in 1962, and the Alzheimer's Disease Research Project started in 1981.
In addition to her work with the institute, Coons served as a lecturer in gerontology in the University of Michigan School of Education, beginning in 1970. By 1978, she had attained the position of Associate Professor. This association reflected Coons' commitment to education and training for people who work with the elderly. She was dedicated to the ideal of creating environments for the elderly in which they would be treated with respect and dignity, and in which they could enjoy homelike comforts, as opposed to being "patients" in a sterile setting. She developed educational materials, published articles, and led workshops, all of which were aimed at understanding the problems of the elderly, and at enlightening those who care for them.
Coons' dedication to her ideals and her commitment to her work have made a strong impact at the University of Michigan and beyond. She has received the University of Michigan Wilbur J. Cohen Award and awards from the Association of Gerontology in Higher Education and the Michigan Non-Profit Homes Association.
The Dorothy H. Coons Papers comprise four series: Professional Papers (1936-1987); Alzheimer's Disease Research Project (1982-1986); Photographs (1966-1972); and Audio-visual Materials (1976-1986). The records cover the years 1936 to 1987, but the bulk of the material falls between 1970 and 1983. Within each series, files are arranged alphabetically by topic.
Subjects:
Hospitals--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Ypsilanti State Hospital.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Hospitals--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Ypsilanti State Hospital.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Professional Papers
  The Professional Papers series (1.2 linear feet) includes materials which relate to her career in the Institute of Gerontology. The "Curriculum Vitae", in Box 1, is helpful in providing context for the rest of the materials. Most of the other materials, including "Correspondence," "Reprints, Reports, and Papers," and "Workshops and Symposia" deal with Coons' research in "milieu therapy," or the concept of the "therapeutic community." Of specific interest in this context is the material covering the "Ypsilanti State Hospital Project", found in Box 2.
  - Clippings 1945-1978 (Box 1)
  - Continuing Education Offerings 1976-1980, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Australia 1980 (Box 1)
    - Dorothea Dix Hospital, Raleigh, N.C. 1975 (Box 1)
    - Hoyt, Elizabeth (N.C.) 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    - Missouri 1980 (Box 1)
    - New Jersey 1980 (Box 1)
    - Ohio 1976-1982 (Box 1)
    - University of Minnesota 1980-1982 (Box 1)
  - "Creativity and Aging" (lecture/concert series)
    - Correspondence and Papers 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    - Publicity 1980 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae 1989 (Box 1)
  - History of UM Institute of Gerontology (IoG) 1936-1980 (Box 1)
  - Images of Old Age in America (exhibition catalog) 1978 (Box 1)
  - IoG Publications List 1949-1980 (Box 1)
  - Multimedia Support Material (Box 1)
    (see Box 3)
  - New England Gerontology Center Summer Institute 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Reprints, Reports and Papers
    - "Companionship Project: A Volunteer Program with the Elderly Homebound," 1975 (Box 1)
    - "Designing a Residential Care Unit for Persons with Dementia," 1987 (Box 1)
    - "Designing a Therapeutic Community for Geriatric Patients," 1973 (Box 1)
    - "Designing a Therapeutic Milieu," 1979 (Box 1)
    - "Expressions of Reality in Old Age," undated (Box 1)
    - "Final Report--Milieu Study," undated (Box 1)
    - "Issues in Long Term Care Settings," (draft) undated (Box 1)
    - "A New Approach to Geriatric Care: The Philosophy and the Model," 1985 (Box 1)
    - "The Process of Change," 1973 (Box 1)
    - "Progress Report II on Milieu Treatment.. .," 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - "Rehabilitation of Geriatric Patients in County Hospitals: A Preliminary Report," 1960 (Box 1)
    - "Report of a Study Tour of European Industrial Therapy Programs," 1963 (Box 1)
    - "Report of a Site Visit to Western Reserve University Habilitation Center," undated (Box 1)
    - "Social Psychiatric Assets and Liabilities Scale for Geriatric Patients," undated (Box 1)
    - "Staff Training: A Powerful Tool for Change," 1975 (Box 1)
    - "A Therapeutic Milieu for Geriatric Patients," 1969 (Box 1)
    - "The Therapeutic Milieu: Social-Psychological Aspects of Treatment," 1983 (Box 1)
    - "Widows and Widowers of Dementia Victims: Their Survival after Spouse's Death," undated (Box 1)
  - Reviews of Books and Media Projects 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - Rone vs. Fireman (expert tour of hospital facility) 1974-1978 (Box 1)
  - Workshops and Symposia 1974-1981
    - "The Aged Disabled and Vocational Rehabilitation" (IoG) 1979 (Box 1)
    - Broughton Hospital, N.C. 1975 (Box 1)
    - Dayton, OH. 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Duke University, Durham, N.C. 1975 (Box 1)
    - Exchange of Practice for Long-Term Care Staff Trainers (IoG Seminar 'E') 1977 (Box 1)
    - Fayetteville State University, Fayetteville, N.C. 1977-1979 (Box 1)
    - Gerontology Workshop, Yankton, S.D. 1974 (Box 1)
      (includes evaluation of IoG media materials)
    - "The Health Specialist's Role in Working with the Elderly" (IoG) 1981 (Box 2)
    - John Umsted Hospital, Butner, N.C. 1975 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Programs 1974-1978 (Box 2)
    - New England Institute for Rehabilitation Research and Education, Inc., Woburn, MA. 1979 (Box 2)
    - "Principles of Milieu Practice" (IoG) 1980 (Box 2)
    - Springfield, MO. 1975-1979 (Box 2)
    - University of Nebraska, Omaha 1974 (Box 2)
  - Ypsilanti State Hospital Project 1962-1971 (Box 2)
- Alzheimer's Disease Research Project
  The Alzheimer's Disease Research Project series (.2 linear feet) consists of records relating to Ms. Coons' research beginning in 1981. Included are "Reprints, Reports and Papers" on Alzheimer's Disease collected and/or produced by Coons; materials relating to the Wesley Hall Project (1981-1986), sponsored by the IoG and Chelsea Methodist Home; and records summarizing a survey of families of Alzheimer's victims.
  - Collected Articles 1982-1984 (Box 2)
  - Purpose and Funding 1982-1985 (Box 2)
  - Reprints, Reports, and Papers
    - Alzheimer's Disease--General (by or about D.H. Coons) 1983 (Box 2)
    - "Alzheimer's Disease: Subjective Experiences of Families," Final Report 1983 (Box 2)
    - "Alzheimer's Disease: Subjective Experiences of Families," Interim Reports 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - "Ann Arbor Foundation Final Report" (Wesley Hall Project) 1984 (Box 2)
    - "A Better Life: Helping Family Members, Volunteers and Staff Improve the Quality of Life of Nursing Home Residents Suffering from Alzheimer's Disease and Related Disorders," 1986 (Box 2)
    - Wesley Hall Project (D.H. Coons articles) 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Survey (Questionnaire, Coding, Data) 1982, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (.1 linear feet), contains 21 photographs in two folders. One image shows Dorothy Coons at the St. Lawrence State Hospital in New York. The other twenty have a significant relationship with the "Ypsilanti State Hospital Project" file, also found in Box 2. They provide a visual record of the efforts of the hospital staff and researchers to provide a pleasing environment for residents.
  - St. Lawrence State Hospital (N.Y.) 1972 (Box 2)
  - Ypsilanti State Hospital Project 1966 (Box 2)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  The Audio-visual Materials series (1 linear foot) contains information in a variety of media--cassette tapes, 16mm films, filmstrips, and two kinds of videotape. Subjects covered include Coons' research in "milieu therapy" and the Wesley Hall Project.
  - Audio Cassette Tapes, March 1976
    - "Aging as a Cultural Process"--by Dr. Carl Brahce (Box 3)
    - "The History of Social Gerontology"--by Dr. Clark Tibbitts (Box 3)
    - Senior Citizens' Advocacy Panel--Woodrow Hunter, moderator (Box 3)
    - "Sociology of Aging"--by Jan Lawrence (Box 3)
    - "The Theory of Community Power"--by Dr. Howard McCluskey (Box 3)
  - Films, 16 mm
    - "Therapeutic Community" (Box 3)
    - "To Live with Dignity" (Box 3)
  - Multimedia Kit
    - "Developing a Therapeutic Community--A Training Series", includes filmstrips and cassette tapes (Box 3)
  - Videotapes
    - "Wesley Hall: A Special Life" 1986, VHS 1/2 inch (Box 3)
    - "Dix Geri Center--Dorothea Dix State Hospital, Raleigh, N.C." circa 1974, 2 Sony V30-H tapes for Helical Scan Video Recorders (Box 3)